Inventory of the Brown, Coalter, Tucker Papers (I) 1780-1929
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
- Group A: Coalter and Tucker Papers, 1780-1858., 6 boxes. (Box 1-6)
  - John Coalter, 1780-1822. (Box 1-3)
    - Box 1 - John Coalter's correspondence with his father, with St. George Tucker, William Munford, and with others until the death of his first wife, Maria Rind, 1780-1793., 221 items. (Box-folder 1:1-60)
      - Samuel Brown, Carlisle, Pennsylvania, to John Coalter, Chesterfield, 5 October 1788. (Box-folder 1:14)
        Samuel Brown gives details of his studies at Dickinson College, and congratulates John Coalter on his chance to study law with St. George Tucker.
      - John Coalter, in Williamsburg to Michael Coalter. January-November 1789., 6 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:15)
        Attending lectures of the Rev. James Madison, President of the College of William and Mary, on Natural Philosophy, and of Mr. Wythe on Law. When John Coalter loses his ribbon he must let his hair hang free for want of money to buy another.
      - Michael Coalter in Augusta to John Coalter, 27 February 1789., 1 letter. ALS. (Box-folder 1:16)
        Two young cousins, in custody of Indians for 3 and 6 years respectively, were freed by the army in Detroit.
      - Michael Coalter in Augusta to John Coalter, September-October 1789., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:17)
      - J[ames] R[ind], in Kentucky, to his sister [Maria Rind] in [Williamsburg], 1 June 1789. (Box-folder 1:18)
        James Rind, had been studying law with St. George Tucker in Williamsburg but left to take a position with "Col. N." Maria Rind remains in the household of St. George Tucker, where she cared for the children.
      - Jacob Kinney, Augusta, to John Coalter, 4 June 1789. (Box-folder 1:19)
        Concerning his wedding trip.
      - Betsy, Jinney, and Peggy Coalter, Augusta, to their brother, John Coalter, June-October 1789., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:20)
      - J. Moore and Elenor Moore, Rockbridge, to their nephew, John Coalter, June-October 1789., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:21)
      - John Grierson Rind, Richmond, to John Coalter, July-November 1789., 3 letters. ALS. Covers lacking. (Box-folder 1:22)
        John Grierson Rind is a brother of Maria Rind. He mentions the need of John Coalter for a coat and a pair of spectacles.
      - John Coalter, at Williamsburg, to his brother Cagy (Micajah) and sister Polly (Mary), August-November 1789., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:23)
      - James Coalter, Ninety-Six, South Carolina and York, Virginia, to his brother John Coalter, Petersburg and Williamsburg, Virginia, September 1789., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:24)
        Approval of the Constitution by South Carolina is still in doubt; threat of an Indian War in Georgia. " Brother Dav[i]d is over in Gloucester. If he has success in purchasing Negroes, I hope we will be ready to sett [sic] out on our rout[e] to the South."
      - "Cousin" to John Coalter, Williamsburg, 6 October 1789. (Box-folder 1:25)
      - John Coalter, in Williamsburg, to his sisters, Betsy, Jinney, and Peggy, 19 October 1789. (Box-folder 1:26)
      - Micajah Coalter, Jr., Augusta, to his brother, John Coalter, 29 October 1789. (Box-folder 1:27)
        First letter of young Micajah Coalter, who is learning to write.
      - Samuel Brown, Staunton, to John Coalter, 4 December 1789. (Box-folder 1:28)
        "Have you been exempted from paying the oppressive Duty which most of our Backwoods Gentlemen have paid for that Knowledge which they have gathered at Williamsburg in Autumn--I mean the loss of Health and a good complexion."
      - Micajah Coalter, Augusta, to John Coalter, January-May 1790., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:29)
        Mentions John Coalter's desire to return home.
      - John Coalter, in Williamsburg, to Michael Coalter, (May) 1790. (Box-folder 1:30)
        Expresses desire to marry and to live on the farm while he is getting started in his law practice.
      - James Rind, in Kentucky, to Maria Rind, 20 May 1790. (Box-folder 1:31)
        "...nothing can be expected without riches...however deserving of a better fate the poor always meet with rudeness and contempt." (Children of a Williamsburg printer, the Rinds were orphaned at an early age and were helped by the Tuckers.)
      - John Coalter, Petersburg, Richmond, Staunton, and Rockbridge, to Maria Rind, in Williamsburg, May-November 1790., 12 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:32)
        His father does not have land to give him at that time, so he cannot marry at once. He has decided to move to Staunton, and continue his studies. In September he writes that he hopes to visit Williamsburg around Christmas, and apply for admission to the bar.
      - Maria Rind, Williamsburg, to John Coalter. June-August 1790., 5 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:33)
        The letters are written with great difficulty, and show a lack of schooling.
      - William Munford, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, 13 June 1790. (Box-folder 1:34)
        Mentions "your quondam charges, Henry, Tudor, Beverley, and Fanny (Tucker) and John and Theodorick Randolph." Hopes he may live and study with Mr. Wythe. "Nothing would advance me faster in the world than the reputation of having been educated by Mr. Wythe, for such a man as he, casts a light upon all around him."
      - St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, 20 July 1790. (Box-folder 1:35)
        John Coalter has borrowed a horse from him for the trip to Staunton.
      - David Coalter, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, to his brother, John Coalter, October 1790., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:36)
        "I...was much pleased to hear of your gallantry but am affeared it has been attended with some accident which occasioned your move to the mountains again..." (Evidently John Coalter did something to protect Maria Rind. He then decided to leave Williamsburg in order to establish himself and be in a position to support her as his wife.)
      - John G. Rind, Richmond, to his sister [Maria Rind], 23 November 1790. (Box-folder 1:37)
      - John Coalter, Richmond, Louisa, Amherst, Augusta, and Staunton, to Maria Rind, March-September 1791., 18 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:38)
        After obtaining his license in Williamsburg, John Coalter has his first case in Amherst. Of St. George Tucker, he writes: "I would rather have the approbation of that man than worlds for my admirers." Advice is given in regard to the torment by John Randolph; plans are made for their marriage in autumn.
      - Maria Rind, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, March-August 1791., 9 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:39)
        In April she writes that Mr. Tucker plans to remarry; she wishes to move up the date of their marriage. She dreads "the prospect of Johnny Randolph returning and you well know, my love, how liable your dear is to be insulted by him..."
      - William Munford, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, April-May 1791., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:40)
        "...thru the surprising friendship of Mr. Wythe, I live in his house and board at his table...In this happy situation tomorrow I begin the Study of Law."
      - John Coalter, Staunton, to James Rind, Williamsburg and Richmond, May-July 1791., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:41)
        Congratulates James Rind on receiving his license to practice law.
      - William Munford, Riveredge, to Maria Rind, May 1791., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:42)
        "We visit very often at the different houses in the neighborhood, at Westover, Nesting, and Shirley, where I saw Robin Carter...we may expect to see you after Mrs. Carter has become Mrs. Tucker."
      - Richard Randolph, Bizarre, to [John Coalter?], June-July 1791., 2 letters. ALS. Covers lacking. (Box-folder 1:43)
        On the return of a wagon and horses; purchases of additional farm animals.
      - William Munford, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, June-August 1791., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:44)
        Living and studying with Mr. Wythe. John Thompson (grandfather of John Thompson Brown) was among the 4th of July orators. Verse and poetic criticism of St. George Tucker. George Wythe is teaching his servant to write.
      - John Coalter, Staunton, to St. George Tucker, June-July 1791., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:45)
        This law practice is discouraging; entrusts Maria Rind to his care, and sends greetings on St. George Tucker's 39th birthday.
      - Samuel Campbell, Bedford County, to John Coalter, August 1791. (Box-folder 1:46)
        Discourages John Coalter from coming "across the Alps" -- there are too many lawyers already.
      - William Munford, Richmond and Riveredge, to John Coalter, September-October 1791., 2 letters. ALS. Covers lacking. (Box-folder 1:47)
        Has moved to Richmond with Mr. Wythe. Mentions building of the canal. Samuel Brown to study in Scotland; congratulates John Coalter on his marriage to Maria Rind.
      - Elizabeth Tucker, Bermuda, to Fanny Tucker, Williamsburg, 30 October 1791. (Box-folder 1:48)
        Elizabeth Tucker is sister of St. George Tucker, and an aunt of Fanny Tucker. Mentions other Tucker children, Henry, Tudor, Beverly, and Elizabeth, as well as Theodorick and Richard Randolph and the latter's wife, Judith. Comments on the proposed marriage of St. George Tucker to Mrs. Carter, and the small children she will be bringing to the marriage.
      - Samuel Brown, Philadelphia, to John Coalter, October-November 1791., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:49)
        Description of George Washington delivering an address in Philadelphia. Congratulates John Coalter on his marriage and sends compliments to his brothers. (This Samuel Brown may be the uncle of John Thompson Brown.)
      - Mrs. Maria Rind Coalter, [Staunton], to Fan [Frances Bland Tucker], [December] 1791. (Box-folder 1:50)
        The letter was written soon after Mrs. Coalter had gone to Staunton with her husband.
      - Mrs. Judith Randolph, Bizarre, to Fanny [Frances Bland Tucker], in Williamsburg, 10 January 1792. (Box-folder 1:51)
        On the marriage of St. George Tucker to Mrs. Lelia (Skipwith) Carter.
      - James Rind, Williamsburg to John Coalter, January-May 1792., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:52)
        Death of Maria Skipwith; the great distress of Mrs. (Lelia Skipwith) Tucker.
      - John G. Rind, Richmond, to Mrs. John Coalter, 1 February 1792. (Box-folder 1:53)
        His wages are to be 15£ or 20£ per year as a clerk.
      - Samuel Brown, Philadelphia and Edinburgh, Pennsylvania, to John Coalter, February-October 1792., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:54)
        The letter from Edinburgh contains an interesting description of life in the Scottish capital, the coldness of his fellow students until they are introduced, and his warm reception by a family to which he had a letter of introduction.
      - William Munford, Richmond, to John Coalter, March-May 1792., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:55)
        Reports that there are about forty students at the College of William and Mary; Theodorick Randolph has died; "Thompson has left W. & M.," and his mother proposes to send him to Harvard.
      - St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, 21 October 1792. (Box-folder 1:56)
        Enquires about Maria, and their expected first child. (Both mother and child died.)
      - John Campbell, Rockingham County, to John Coalter, 26 January 1793. (Box-folder 1:57)
      - David Coalter, Orangeburg and Columbia, South Carolina, to John Coalter, February-December 1793., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 1:58)
        The "distressing news" that his wife has died in childbirth.
      - John G. Rind, Richmond, to John Coalter, 11 May 1793. (Box-folder 1:59)
        War reports; the parade of the Richmond Grenadiers, Light Horse and Light Infantry.
      - William Munford, Riveredge to John Coalter, 28 August 1793. (Box-folder 1:60)
        Consoles John Coalter on the loss of his wife; reports the Independence Day orations at the College of William and Mary, and mentions the raising of subscriptions to aid distressed French immigrants at Norfolk.
    - Box 2 - Correspondence of John Coalter during his second marriage to Margaret Davenport, and in the early years of his third marriage, to Frances Bland Tucker. Correspondence from St. George Tucker, Mrs. Lelia Tucker, Mrs. Judith Randolph, and others, 1793-1808., 164 items. (Box-folder 2:1-70)
      The contents of Box 2 trace the legal career of John Coalter from 10 April 1795, when St. George Tucker recommended him for the position of Clerk of the Court in Staunton, through the period of his second and third marriages to Margaret Davenport, 1795 (she died in 1797), and to Frances Bland Tucker, 1802.
      Included also are letters to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter from her father St. George Tucker, her stepmother Mrs. Lelia Skipwith Tucker, her sister-in-law Mrs. Judith Randolph of Bizarre, and others. Correspondence with William Munford, in Williamsburg, is also included.
      - St. George Tucker, Charlottesville, to John. Tyler and others, 10 April 1793. (Box-folder 2:1)
        Recommends John Coalter as Clerk of the Staunton Court.
      - John Coalter, Charlottesville, to Peggy (Margaret) Davenport, in Williamsburg, 17 April 1793. (Box-folder 2:2)
        "Yes, Peggy, my Maria is gone! The worst of evils has befallen your friend."
      - R. Whiting, New York, to John Coalter, 1 November 1793. (Box-folder 2:3)
        Requests payment of a debt.
      - James C[oalter], Orangeburg, South Carolina, to John Coalter, 8 December 1793. (Box-folder 2:4)
      - William Munford, to John Coalter, 13 December 1793., ALS. (Box-folder 2:5)
        William Munford has returned to the College of William and Mary, and is "in constant attendance on Mr. (St. George) Tucker...Mrs. Tucker has lately been so unfortunate as to lose a newborn child."
      - Exchange of letters between Jenny Stuart and John Coalter, January-June 1794., 4 letters. ALS. Covers lacking. (Box-folder 2:6)
        Accuses John Coalter of "making a stroke at her character"; makes insulting statements regarding John Coalter's late wife. John Coalter responds by threatening to take Jenny Stuart into court, after which she offers to return John Coalter's letter.
      - James Coalter, Charlestown, South Carolina, to John Coalter, 1 February 1794 (Box-folder 2:7)
        James Coalter is a merchant, dealing largely in indigo.
      - William Munford, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, 20 April 1794. (Box-folder 2:8)
        Recounts a voyage to Hampton Roads to view the French Fleet, consisting of 150 ships, including three men of war, five or six frigates, and armed merchantmen laden with flour. Party spirit in Norfolk; Aristocrats more prominent; acrimony inflamed by the presence of the French fleet and a British frigate. William Munford is ready to apply for his law license.
      - M[argaret] D[avenport] to F. Currie, 25 May 1794. (Box-folder 2:9)
        "There can be but one in the world" for her, but he is "out of her reach." At a recent dinner the first toast by Governor Lee was to her.
      - F. H. C[urry], North of Louisa, to Mrs. Margaret Davenport Coalter, Williamsburg, 15 February 1795., ALS. (Box-folder 2:10)
        Congratulations on the occasion of her marriage to John Coalter.
      - John Coalter, Staunton, to Mrs. Coalter, February-May 1795., 14 Letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:11)
        The difficulty of finding passage for Mrs. Coalter and her mother from Williamsburg to Staunton. John Coalter is finally able to borrow a phaeton which he has overhauled and supplied with an umbrella. Advice regarding divorce of F. C[?]y.
      - D. Holmes, Harrisburg, to John Coalter, 2 May 1795. (Box-folder 2:12)
        Concerning a mare to be serviced.
      - Mrs. Coalter, Williamsburg to John Coalter, 10 May 1795. (Box-folder 2:13)
      - [Mrs. Coalter to John Coalter], 3 August 1795. (Box-folder 2:14)
      - John Coalter, Botetourt, to Mrs. Coalter, [August] 1795. (Box-folder 2:15)
      - J[ames] Brown, Danville, Kentucky, to John Coalter, 10 December 1795. (Box-folder 2:16)
        The "war" and Indian victory are mentioned and a bloody spring season is predicted.
      - John Coalter, Orangeburg, South Carolina and Louisville, Georgia, to Mrs. Coalter, January 1796., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:17)
        Divorce proceedings for a Mrs. Matthews before the Georgia Legislature.
      - F. H. A[llison], Cabin Point, to Mrs. Coalter, 15 July 1797. (Box-folder 2:18)
        Mention is made of a child expected by Mrs. Coalter.
      - David Coalter, Orangeburg, South Carolina, to John Coalter, 19 August 1797. (Box-folder 2:19)
        Condolences "on this distressing occasion" (the death of John Coalter's wife in childbirth; the child also died.)
      - James Coalter, Ninety-Six, South Carolina, to John Coalter, 9 June 1797., ALS. (Box-folder 2:20)
        Business letter concerning collections to be made in Virginia.
      - Mrs. Lucy Randolph, at Curles, to Ann Frances Tucker, 2 December 1798. (Box-folder 2:21)
        She should "by this time be fatigued with the name of Tucker" and that she "had better look about" (for a husband).
      - ( ) Davenport, Williamsburg, to [John Coalter], February 1799. (Box-folder 2:22)
        The letter is from the papers of John Coalter.
      - Lelia Anna Byrd, Riveredge, to Frances Tucker, 12 April 1801. (Box-folder 2:23)
      - Mrs. Judith Randolph, Farmville, [Bizarre], to Frances Tucker, May-June 1801., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:24)
        Judith Randolph, wife of Richard Randolph, half brother of Frances Tucker, sends greetings to Polly and Charles (Carter), step-sister and brother of Frances Tucker. The "Mama" mentioned is Mrs. Lelia Carter Tucker.
      - St. George Tucker, Winchester, to John Coalter, 14 August 1801. (Box-folder 2:25)
      - Mrs. Judith Randolph, Farmville, to Frances [Bland] Tucker, 6 February 1802. (Box-folder 2:26)
        Complains that she is "surrounded by the real evils of life." (Her husband had been linked with her sister in the famous scandal proceedings.)
      - David Coalter, Fredericksburg, to John Coalter, 28 April 1802. (Box-folder 2:27)
        Concerning a horse in which he is interested.
      - B. W. Leigh, Chesterfield, to Frances Tucker, 28 May 1802. (Box-folder 2:28)
        Hint of a June wedding for Frances Tucker.
      - Anne H. Nicholas, Swans Point, to Mrs. Fanny B. [Tucker] Coalter, 30 June 1802., ALS. (Box-folder 2:29)
        Fanny B. Tucker has just married John Coalter and returned with him to Staunton. Anne H. Nicholas writes that Lelia Byrd has died at the age of 18.
      - Mrs. Lelia Tucker, Williamsburg, to her stepdaughter, Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, 13 July 1802. (Box-folder 2:30)
      - Mrs. Judith Randolph, Farmville, to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, 29 August 1802. (Box-folder 2:31)
      - John Coalter, Elm Grove and Lexington, to his wife. August-September 1802., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:32)
        Elm Grove was the new home of the Coalters. Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter was in the Warm Springs for her health in September.
      - Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, [Warm Springs], to John Coalter, 6 October 1802. (Box-folder 2:33)
      - St. George Tucker, Richmond, to John Coalter, 14 November 1802. (Box-folder 2:34)
      - Mrs. Ann Coalter, Orangeburg, South Carolina, to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, 4 December 1802. (Box-folder 2:35)
      - John Coalter, Richmond, Elm Grove, and Lexington, to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, January-August 1803., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:36)
        Frances Bland Tucker Coalter returns to Williamsburg for the birth of her first child, Francis Lelia; the burning of the buildings of Lexington Academy.
      - St. George Tucker and Mrs. Lelia Tucker, Williamsburg, Haymarket, and Fredericksburg, to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, June-October 1803., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:37)
      - Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, Warm Springs, to John Coalter, 20 August 1803. (Box-folder 2:38)
      - Mrs. Judith Randolph, Farmville, to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, 31 August 1803. (Box-folder 2:39)
      - St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, January 1804., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:40)
      - Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, Elm Grove, to John Coalter, March, April 1804., 3 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:41)
        John Coalter was on the court circuit.
      - John Coalter, Botetourt and Natural Bridge, to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, [March, April] 1804., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:42)
        The letters are undated, but are replies to those from Frances Bland Tucker Coalter to John Coalter.
      - Mrs. Judith Randolph to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, September 1804., 2 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:43)
      - Mrs. F. D[avenport], Richmond, to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, 5 November 1804. (Box-folder 2:44)
        F. Davenport was the mother of the second wife of John Coalter, who continued to live with the Coalters.
      - St. George Tucker, Williamsburg. Endorsement on letter from B. W. Leigh, Petersburg, 10 February 1805. (Box-folder 2:45)
        Concerning deed to property, probably Elm Grove, the home bought by John Coalter.
      - St. George Tucker and Maria Carter, Williamsburg, to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, 9 April 1805. (Box-folder 2:46)
        Maria Carter was a step-daughter of St. George Tucker.
      - James Davenport, Chillicothe, Ohio, to John Coalter, 13 April 1805. (Box-folder 2:47)
        Writes of obtaining a clerk's position with the Ohio Assembly at $4.00 per day.
      - Mrs. Judith Randolph, Bizarre, to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, April-December 1805., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:48)
        Death of her husband and her straitened circumstances; Bizarre in bad condition; hopes to send her son, St. George, to Europe to cure his deafness.
      - St. George Tucker, Richmond and Williamsburg, to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, April-June 1805., 5 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:49)
        In June, St. George Tucker and Mrs. Tucker set out for Staunton in order to be there for the lying-in of Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter.
      - Mrs. Tucker, Williamsburg, to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, April-December 1805., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:50)
        First mention of the second Coalter child, Elizabeth.
      - M[argaret] Coalter, Bizarre, to John Coalter, 20 April 1805. (Box-folder 2:51)
        The illness of Tudor Randolph.
      - David Coalter, Orangeburg, South Carolina, to John Coalter, 28 July 1805. (Box-folder 2:52)
        Congratulates John Coalter on the birth of his second daughter and the purchase of Elm Grove. He writes at length about the difficulty in buying good house servants.
      - St. George Tucker and Mrs. Tucker, Williamsburg, to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, January-November 1806., 5 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:53)
      - St. George Tucker, Williamsburg, to John Coalter, January-May 1806., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:54)
        Financial matters, mainly about bank shares and dividends.
      - Mrs. Judith Randolph, Hayes and Bizarre, to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, March-October 1806., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:55)
        St. George Randolph's visit to England; her disappointment over continued his deafness Dr. Cooper says "occasioned by the irruption of his ears at nine months old." Has no authority over the servants. Illness of Polly the seamstress.
      - John Coalter, Charlottesville, to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, April (and after) 1806., 4 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:56)
      - St. George Tucker and Mrs. Tucker, Wmsbg, to Mrs. Frances Bland Tucker Coalter, January-December 1807., 12 letters. ALS. (Box-folder 2:57)